Samuel Berger Tufts Memorabilia Collection MS159
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Samuel Berger Tufts Memorabilia Collection
1856 -- 2005
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Berger, Samuel Harry
MS159
14.55 Linear Feet 6 oversize boxes, 1 record carton, 1 letter box, 3 volumes, 5 reel containers
3 Volumes
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into two series: Artifacts; and Visual Materials and Ephemera.
Biographical / Historical
Dr. Samuel Harry Berger (1948-2009), M'73, known warmly as Sam or Sammy to most people, grew up in Queens, New York, where his interest in medicine began at Queens College. He completed the pre-med curriculum with honors and actively participated in Alpha Epsilon Pi fraternity. He and his wife, Marlene, traveled to Boston, MA, where Sam graduated from Tufts University School of Medicine. Sam completed medical training in Pediatrics at Albert Einstein College Of Medicine of Yeshiva University in Bronx, NY. His family settled in Rockland County, New York where he worked as a pediatrician for 30 years. Sam's professional affiliations extended to Columbia Presbyterian Medical Center, where he was assistant clinical professor (1997 - 2001). He joined and then headed a pediatric practice in Bardonia, NY and treated children at Nyack Hospital in Nyack, NY as a staff physician in pediatrics. In November 2006, the Pediatric Society of Rockland County recognized Sam for 30 years of distinguished, dedicated, and excellent service. Sam was an avid memorabilia collector with his primary collection consisting of significant pieces related to Willie Mays' Hall-of-Fame baseball career. Because of the strong connection he developed with Tufts during his years in medical school, he began collecting Tufts memorabilia related to all of Tufts' schools and colleges and became well versed in the history of the university. Dr. Berger passed away on January 19, 2009, and is survived by his wife, Marlene Berger, and his two daughters, Emily Berger (Tufts J'03, M'08) and Mara Erickson. Marlene Berger generously donated her husband's collection of Tufts memorabilia to Tufts Digital Collections and Archives in 2013.
Custodial History
This collection is comprised of an aggregation of Tufts memorabilia and Tufts- related items largely purchased by Samuel Berger. The collection was donated in two accessions by Samuel Berger and family.
Scope and Contents
This collection comprises Tufts and Tufts-related memorabilia collected by alumnus Samuel Berger. Materials include sports tickets and programs, publications, photographs, and postcards. Most items date from the early and mid-twentieth century. Many items include representations of Tufts buildings, the Tufts seal, and/or Jumbo, or are items commemorating class years, teams, or clubs at Tufts.
Alumni collections; University history
- Artifacts, 1900 -- 2000; MS159.001; 3.1 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains Tufts memorabilia including paperweights, pins and charms, dinnerware, ashtrays, pennants, a canvas bag, and a football jersey. Most items date from the early and mid-twentieth century, and feature images of Tufts buildings (primarily Ballou Hall, Goddard Chapel, and Eaton Memorial Library), the Tufts seal, and/or representations of Jumbo. Some of the material, including the canvas bag and pins, are items commemorating class years at Tufts.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged loosely chronologically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Circular acknowlegement paperweight, 1950 -- 2000; MS159.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
    Inscribed "In grateful acknowledgment Leadership and Service"
  - Gold clip with Tuftonian charm, 1930 -- 1980; MS159.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Tufts Jumbos pin, 1940 -- 1990; MS159.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - Ballou Hall Alumni Day pin, 1941-06-14; MS159.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - Goddard Chapel paperweight, 1910 -- 1960; MS159.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
  - Tufts football pin, 1910 -- 1960; MS159.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
    Made by Ehrman Manufacturing Co
  - Tufts cufflinks, 1920 -- 1970; MS159.001.001.00007 (Box 1)
  - Jumbo charm bracelet, 1934; MS159.001.001.00008 (Box 1)
  - Tufts pen and pencil set, 1920 -- 1970; MS159.001.001.00009 (Box 1)
  - Tufts pin with football charm, 1930 -- 1980; MS159.001.001.00010 (Box 1)
  - Sterling enamel Tufts University charm, 1940 -- 1990; MS159.001.001.00011 (Box 1)
  - Wedgwood plate with Jumbo, 1910 -- 1960; MS159.001.001.00012 (Box 1)
  - Tufts Hyde Park No. 1900 Ashtray, 1940 -- 1990; MS159.001.002.00001 (Box 2)
  - Tufts clear ashtray, 1940 -- 1990; MS159.001.002.00002 (Box 2)
  - Goddard Chapel tea cup and saucer, 1910 -- 1960; MS159.001.003.00001 (Box 3)
  - Tufts black mug, 1950 -- 2000; MS159.001.003.00002 (Box 3)
  - Tufts bookends, 1950 -- 2000; MS159.001.003.00003 (Box 3)
  - Tufts beer stein, 1940 -- 1990; MS159.001.003.00004 (Box 3)
  - Tufts Class of 1937 reunion sign, 1940 -- 1990; MS159.001.003.00005 (Box 3)
  - Tufts Class of 1937 dunce cap, 1940 -- 1990; MS159.001.003.00006 (Box 3)
  - Tufts pewter plate, 1930 -- 1980; MS159.001.003.00007 (Box 3)
  - Goddard Chapel plate, 1932; MS159.001.004.00001 (Box 4)
  - Ballou Hall plate, 1947; MS159.001.005.00001 (Box 5)
  - The College Ediface plate, 1957; MS159.001.006.00001 (Box 6)
  - The College Ediface plate, 1957; MS159.001.007.00001 (Box 7)
  - Tufts Graduation Pin, 1978; MS159.001.008.00001 (Box MS159 Shared 1)
  - Pocket knife with Tufts crest, 1910; MS159.001.008.00002 (Box MS159 Shared 1)
  - Tufts Basketball Tournament charm, 1924; MS159.001.008.00003 (Box MS159 Shared 1)
  - Tufts brown and blue pennant, 1915; MS159.001.008.00004 (Box MS159 Shared 1)
  - Tufts pennant with crest, 1915; MS159.001.008.00005 (Box MS159 Shared 1)
  - Tufts pennant with fighting Jumbo, 1960; MS159.001.008.00006 (Box MS159 Shared 1)
  - Tufts pennant with walking Jumbo, 1960; MS159.001.008.00007 (Box MS159 Shared 1)
  - Brown and white pennant with Tufts crest, 1960; MS159.001.008.00008 (Box MS159 Shared 1)
  - Tufts pennant with football player, 1960; MS159.001.008.00009 (Box MS159 Shared 1)
  - Small Tufts pennant, 1960; MS159.001.008.00010 (Box MS159 Shared 1)
  - Tufts pennant with five fighting Jumbos, 1960; MS159.001.008.00011 (Box MS159 Shared 1)
  - Pin with Tufts seal, 1930 -- 1940; MS159.001.008.00012 (Box MS159 Shared 1)
  - Tufts Alumni Day pin with Ballou Hall, 1941-06-14; MS159.001.010.00001 (Box 10)
  - Ashtray with Tufts seal, 1937; MS159.001.010.00002 (Box 10)
    Set of two
  - Coaster with Tufts seal, 1910 -- 1960; MS159.001.010.00003 (Box 10)
    Set of four
  - Coaster with Harvard seal, 1910 -- 1960; MS159.001.010.00004 (Box 10)
    Set of three
  - Ashtray with Jumbo, 1910 -- 1960; MS159.001.010.00005 (Box 10)
  - Paperweight with Tufts seal, 1950 -- 2000; MS159.001.010.00006 (Box 10)
  - Cigarette case with Tufts seal, 1900 -- 1950; MS159.001.010.00007 (Box 10)
  - Decorative Tufts College tile with Ballou Hall and Chapel, 1920 -- 1970; MS159.001.010.00008 (Box 10)
  - Class of 1944 canvas bag, 1950 -- 2000; MS159.001.010.00009 (Box 10)
  - Tufts jersey #73, 1910 -- 1960; MS159.001.010.00010 (Box 10)
  - Goddard Chapel plate, 1932; MS159.001.011.00001 (Box 11)
  - Ballou Hall plate, 1950; MS159.001.011.00002 (Box 11)
  - Eaton Memorial Library plate, 1950; MS159.001.011.00003 (Box 11)
  - Satchel with Tufts decal, 1920 -- 1970; MS159.001.012.00001 (Box 12)
  - Felt and fabric bag with Jumbo, 1950 -- 2000; MS159.001.012.00002 (Box 12)
  - Goddard Chapel wooden box, 1900 -- 1950; MS159.001.013.00001 (Box 13)
- Visual Materials and Ephemera, 1856 -- 2005; MS159.002; 0.55 Linear Feet
  This series contains sports tickets and programs, early athletics letter patches, photographs, postcards, Tufts and Tufts-related publications, and small Tufts memorabilia such as ribbons, stickers, and matchbook covers. Most items date from the early and mid-twentieth century. Sports tickets and programs are primarily for football events (with one program for baseball and one for track and field), and early athletics latter patches include baseball, swimming, track, tennis, football, basketball, fencing, rowing, and hockey. Photographs largely document athletic teams, clubs, and organizations (including the Louis Pasteur club and the Officers of Student Army Training Corps), and Tufts buildings. Some postcards have been written on and sent while others are blank; the bulk of postcards contain representations of Tufts buildings. Tufts-related publications include newspapers and books that make mention or contain images of Tufts or Tufts students and faculty,and Tufts publications include newspapers, viewbooks, programs, and calendars. Patches, ribbons, stickers, and matchbook covers include representations of the Tufts seal, the Tufts flag, Jumbo, and the flags of other institutions such as Colgate, Yale, Case Western, CCNY, etc.
  - Ballou's Pictorial, 1856-10-11; MS159.002.008.00001 (Box MS159 Shared 1)
  - Ballou Hall print, 1870; MS159.002.008.00002 (Box MS159 Shared 1)
  - Leslie's Weekly, 1902-05-01; MS159.002.008.00003 (Box MS159 Shared 1)
  - Tufts College wall calendar, 1906; MS159.002.008.00004 (Box MS159 Shared 1)
  - Class of 1908 Freshman Banquet pamphlet, 1905; MS159.002.008.00005 (Box MS159 Shared 1)
  - Tufts song book, 1909; MS159.002.008.00006 (Box MS159 Shared 1)
  - Officers of Student Army Training Corps Tufts College, 1918; MS159.002.008.00007 (Box MS159 Shared 1)
  - Tufts class photo, in uniform, 1918; MS159.002.008.00008 (Box MS159 Shared 1)
  - Tufts "Brown and Blue" song poster, 1920; MS159.002.008.00009 (Box MS159 Shared 1)
  - Tufts wall calendar, 1924; MS159.002.008.00010 (Box MS159 Shared 1)
  - Communion Breakfast of Louis Pasteur Club of Tufts College, 1924; MS159.002.008.00011 (Box MS159 Shared 1)
  - Postcards, 1900 -- 1909; MS159.002.009.00001 (Box 9)
  - Postcards, 1910 -- 1919; MS159.002.009.00002 (Box 9)
  - Postcards, 1920 -- 1929; MS159.002.009.00003 (Box 9)
  - Postcards, 1930 -- 1939; MS159.002.009.00004 (Box 9)
  - Postcards, 1940 -- 1949; MS159.002.009.00005 (Box 9)
  - Postcards, 1950 -- 1959; MS159.002.009.00006 (Box 9)
  - Postcards, 1960 -- 1969; MS159.002.009.00007 (Box 9)
  - Undated postcards, 1900 -- 1980; MS159.002.009.00008 (Box 9)
  - Medical School class photograph, 1904; MS159.002.009.00009 (Box Shared 38)
  - Tufts patches, 1930 -- 1980; MS159.002.009.00010 (Box 9)
    Tufts seal, fighting Jumbo, Honor Guard
  - Leather patches, 1910 -- 1960; MS159.002.009.00011 (Box 9)
    Tufts seal, Tufts flag, other institutions (Colgate, Yale, Case Western, CCNY, etc)
  - Ribbons and small pennants, 1910 -- 1960; MS159.002.009.00012 (Box 9)
    Tufts flag, Tufts seal, Brown and Blue song
  - Stickers and matchbook covers, 1910 -- 1960; MS159.002.009.00013 (Box 9)
    Tufts seal, fighting Jumbo
  - Early athletics letter patches, 1900 -- 1950; MS159.002.009.00014 (Box 9)
    Baseball, swimming, track, tennis, football, basketball, fencing, rowing, hockey, etc
  - Tickets and programs, 1905 -- 1926; MS159.002.009.00015 (Box 9)
    Class Day tickets, football schedule, medical school dance program and handbook
  - Photographs, 1860 -- 1920; MS159.002.009.00016 (Box 9)
    Train station, athletics, Tufts buildings, etc
  - Youth's Companion, 1912-03-21; MS159.002.009.00017 (Box 9)
    Page of newspaper with advertisement for Jackson College for Women
  - Boston: 150 Views, 1920; MS159.002.009.00018 (Box 9)
    Image of Radcliffe College Tufts Medical School
  - Alumni Day map, 1929; MS159.002.009.00019 (Box 9)
  - Tufts Alumni Admissions Program (TAAP) Handbook for Interviewers, 2003 -- 2005; MS159.002.009.00020 (Box 9)
  - Tufts Preview, 2001; MS159.002.009.00021 (Box 9)
  - Track and field, Tufts vs. University of Maine, 1906-05-05; MS159.002.009.00022 (Box 9)
  - Football, Tufts vs. Boston University, 1927-10-29; MS159.002.009.00023 (Box 9)
  - Football, Tufts vs. Middlebury, 1928-11-10; MS159.002.009.00024 (Box 9)
  - Baseball, Tufts vs. Lowell Textile, 1939-04-21; MS159.002.009.00025 (Box 9)
  - Football, Tufts vs. Harvard, 1945-10-06; MS159.002.009.00026 (Box 9)
  - Football, Tufts vs. Boston University, 1945-10-20; MS159.002.009.00027 (Box 9)
  - Football, Tufts vs. Harvard, 1946-10-05; MS159.002.009.00028 (Box 9)
  - Tufts Colleges of Liberal Arts and Engineering Viewbook, 1930 -- 1960; MS159.002.009.00029 (Box 9)
  - Centennial Celebration Program, 1952-10-11 -- 1952-10-12; MS159.002.009.00030 (Box 9)
  - "Tufts College: Its Science and Technology, A Centennial View" lecture by Leonard Carmichael, 1952; MS159.002.009.00031 (Box 9)
  - Along the Row at Tufts College, 1944; MS159.002.009.00032 (Box 9)
  - Along the Row calendar, 1947; MS159.002.009.00033 (Box 9)
  - One Hour of Medical History, Volume II, 1932; MS159.002.009.00034 (Box Volume 9)
  - One Hour of Medical History, Volume III, 1934; MS159.002.009.00035 (Box Volume 9)
  - Tufts University, 1988; MS159.002.009.00036; Azzi, Robert; Butler, William (Box Volume 9)
    Copy number 170 in blue slipcase; Donated by Dr. Samuel Berger; Accession 2010.010; A book of photographs of Tufts University. Prospect, Kentucky: Harmony House, 1988.